Suraj Suresh

346-467-5967 | surajsuresh27@gmail.com | www.linkedin.com/in/surajsuresh94 | Arlington, TX

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY:

Skilled IT professional with 5+ years of experience in software development using JAVA, Python, automation testing and data analysis. Experienced with network and cloud technologies and possessing excellent problem-solving and troubleshooting skills. Hungry to learn more and apply my skills to continually innovate and improve.

EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICATION

MS in Information Systems, Data Analytics/ Data Science Specialization
University of Texas at Arlington, Arlington, TX
GPA: 3.8

Master of Computer Applications
PES Institute of Technology, Bangalore, India
GPA: 3.6

Bachelor of Computer Applications
New Horizon College, Bangalore, India
GPA: 3.7

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: Java, Python, C++

Web Technologies: HTML5, CSS3, PHP, JavaScript

Database: MySQL, SQLite

Tools: BI: Tableau (Tableau Certified Data Analyst), Alteryx (Designer Core Certified), SAP Hana | Cloud: AWS | Google

Cybersecurity Professional Certification

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Developer/Engineer

July 2018 - Dec 2021

100Pi Labs, Bangalore, India

- Developed Android applications using JAVA. Worked on multiple code refactors, switching from JAVA to Kotlin on some activities.
- Trained a team of junior engineers on the Selenium/Espresso framework for Android automation testing.
- Lead the development and deployment of features of multiple top rated Android applications with over 65 million downloads such as Pi Music Player, Pi Video Player.
- Worked on the integration YouTube features onto the app using licensed YouTube APIs and parsing JSON files using JAVA to display global content based on region.
- Designed app store assets using Adobe Photoshop and handling SEO and ASO of these apps.
- Debugged and deployed fixes for customer issues logged onto GitLab. Handled git version control by handling merges, commits, branches and presiding over code reviews.
- Developed a user manual website using HTML5 and CSS3.
- Added events and event loggers into code to monitor user behavior and activities.
- Ran version-based deployment experiments on Google Play Console to A/B test different features based on region, Android version etc.
- Worked on the migration from BitBucket (Atlassian) to GitLab.
- Quality Assurance and Testing of newer app versions and fixes before deployment.

Data Engineer Sept 2019 - Dec 2021

100Pi Labs, Bangalore, India

- Analyzed data from various platforms like Firebase, Google Play Console, Facebook analytics to develop actionable insights to improve user acquisition and retention.
- Gathered data through ETL pipelines from various analytics platforms and compiled reports and dashboards using Tableau to provide detailed overview of app metrics, usage metrics. Used Tableau stories to convey information for easier data ingestion.
- Monitored programmed events to identify areas of interest within the apps, track user activity and gather data in compliance with GDPR to prioritize fixes and integration of newer features in-app.
- Analyzed Data on Google Play Console, Facebook Analytics and Google Firebase to monitor KPI and using keyword analytics to drive more downloads. Contributed to the increase in DAU and downloads from 10 million in 2018 to 53 million in 2020. Used predictive analytics to predict user trends and potential usage growth using historical data.
- Performed keyword analytics from tools like App Annie, Sensor Tower to identify key trends in keyword usage for SEO and ASO.

University of Texas at Arlington - Libraries, Arlington, TX

- Worked on **BitCurator** to test, error-check and make digital preservation copies of legacy born digital media.
- Python scripts to automate encoding of finding aids into XMLs and metadata files to upload on TARO, Preservica and UTA
 Libraries Digital Gallery.
- · Crawled web pages for preservation and performing Quality Assurance on crawl reports on Archive-It.
- Worked towards the implementation of **Archive Space** for the UTA Digital Archives and Special Collections.

ACADEMIC/WORK PROJECTS

Automatic Detection and Classification of Growth Phases of a Bacterial Cell Duration

(MATLAB)

Used MATLAB to report on a rapid method for reagent less identification and discrimination of single celled bacteria using edge detection and basic morphology. Developed and automated a system that could analyze digital images of a bacteria and classify the bacterial growth phases by identifying geometric features of the bacterial cell.

Human Resource Management System

(ASP.NET using C#, MySQL server)

Developed front-end of a HRMS web application using C# on ASP.NET and back-end using MySQL server. Worked on implementation and addition of incremental updates and features such as including Google APIs for geo clock-in clock out, auto payroll etc. Worked on two separate modules of Employee and Admin

Title: Online Vehicle Showroom

(PHP,HTML, AJAX, JavaScript, MySQL)

Developed a virtual showroom web application using multiple web technologies like PHP, HTML and AJAX for widget UI's and JavaScript, SQL for handling store databases and functionality. Worked on WYSIWYG web builder to develop custom UI templates and wireframes prior to development of final build.